Testimonios: Documenting the Lives and Faith of Latino Immigrants 2001-2002 ohrc104
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Testimonios: Documenting the Lives and Faith of Latino Immigrants
2001-2002
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory
ohrc104
11 Interviews Audio files, transcripts, and collateral materials
The project deals with Latino immigrants, most of whom are from Mexico and have settled in and around Indianapolis, Indiana. The interviewees discuss immigrating, transitioning into life in the United States, the important role religion--Catholicism in particular--plays in their lives, and the active role they take in their communities. Most of the transcribed interviews are in Spanish.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains eleven interviews conducted over one year. The interviews range from thirty to ninety-five minutes. All interviews consist of audio tapes and most have typed transcripts in Spanish.
Acquisition Information
Oral history interviews conducted by the Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory from 1968 to the present, with particular focus on the history of twentieth-century America and the Midwest.
- Aguayo, Norberto; Aguayo, Maria Teresa, March 3, 2002; 02-059; Sharp, Ethan; 8 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 35 minutes; index; transcribed in Spanish
  Access Status
  Open
  Scope and Content Note
  Maria Teresa Aguayo and her husband Norberto Aguayo, talk about their immigration to Indiana from Mexico. They discuss their activities through the Hispanic ministries of St. Patrick Catholic Church. They discuss the difficulties of their transition into life in the United States. The Aguayos also discuss their involvement in the pro-life movement.
  Indianapolis, Indiana; Mexico; Catholic church; immigration; Latino communities; pro-life movement; St. Patrick Catholic Church
- Aguilera, Vicente, June 7, 2002; 02-070; Sharp, Ethan; 12 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index; transcribed in Spanish
  Vicente Aguilera tells about his immigration from Mexico to Indiana, his experiences as a migrant worker in Whiteland, and his different jobs and struggles in Indianapolis. He talks about his marriage, the births of his daughters, the death of his wife, and his second marriage. He discusses a prolonged sickness that he suffered, and his healing. He talks about his conversion to evangelical Christianity, his role as a pastor, and his association with the international organization Pentecostal Church of God.
  pastor; Indianapolis, Indiana; Mexico; immigration; Latino communities; Migrant Workers; Templo Betel Church
- Amezcua, Javier, January 31, 2002; 02-058; Sharp, Ethan; 12 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 50 minutes; index; transcribed in Spanish
  Javier Amezcua talks about his immigration to the United States from Mexico, his move to Indianapolis, Indiana, and his first jobs there. He tells the history of his restaurant. Amezcua talks about the Catholic church, his participation in the festivities of Our Lady of Guadalupe, and the lack of Spanish masses. He also discusses his role in Alianza Mexicana (Mexican Alliance).
  restaurant owner; Indianapolis, Indiana; Mexico; Catholicism; immigration; Latino communities; Mexican restaurants; Mexican Alliance of Indiana
- Imán, Ricardo, April 30, 2002; 02-065; Sharp, Ethan; 11 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 50 minutes; index; transcribed in Spanish
  Ricardo Imán tells about his education and life as a member of the order of Hermanos De La Salle (De La Salle Christian Brothers) in Mexico. He discusses his move to Indiana and his role in Hispanic Catholic ministries. Imán discusses his perceptions of the Latino communities and of the Catholic church.
  teacher; Indianapolis, Indiana; Mexico; Catholicism; immigration; Latino communities; De La Salle Christian Brothers; St. Mary Catholic Church; St. Monica Catholic Church; St. Patrick Catholic Church; O'Mara, Michael
- Morales, Evangelina, April 9, 2002; 02-062; Sharp, Ethan; 14 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index; transcribed in Spanish
  Eva Morales tells about her life in Mexico, her marriage, her move to the United States, and her life in Indianapolis, Indiana, where she finally settled. She discusses her involvement in Mexican-American civic associations, the Hispanic Center, Fiesta Indianapolis, and the Catholic church. Morales discusses the beginnings and growth of the Hispanic ministries at St. Patrick Catholic Church, and the roles of both herself and her husband in the church. She also discusses her experiences with learning English.
  educator; Indianapolis, Indiana; Mexico; Catholicism; immigration; Latino communities; Hispanic Center of Indianapolis; St. Mary Catholic Church; St. Patrick Catholic Church; Wishard Memorial Hospital Hispanic Services; Espinoza; Duffy, Mary Kay; Fox, Tom
- Quiroz, Consuelo E., June 5, 2002; 02-069; Sharp, Ethan; 13 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index
  Consuelo Espinoza Quiroz discusses her early life and education. She talks about her family as a child and as an adult. She discusses migration from Texas to Indiana and what a transition it was. She discusses her involvement in the Catholic church, the Spanish services, and the importance of her faith. Quiroz talks about jobs that she's held and opening her own beauty salon. She also tells about her experiences with racism.
  Indianapolis, Indiana; Mexico; Texas; Catholicism; family; Latino communities; Migrant Workers; migration; St. Mary Catholic Church; St. Patrick Catholic Church; Fox, Tom; Morales, Evangelina
- Sanchez, Luis, April 4, 2002; 02-061; Sharp, Ethan; 11 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 55 minutes; index; transcribed in Spanish
  Luis Sanchez tells about his studies and professional life in Colombia, his move to the United States, and his jobs in Indianapolis, Indiana. He discusses his involvement in St. Patrick Catholic Church, explains the evolution of his faith, and offers his perceptions of the Catholic church and the Latino communities in Indianapolis.
  restaurant worker; Colombia; Indianapolis, Indiana; Catholicism; immigration; Latino communities; St. Patrick Catholic Church
- Tapia, Maria, April 12, 2002; 02-063; Sharp, Ethan; 13 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 50 minutes; index
  Maria Tapia discusses immigrating to East Chicago, Indiana from Mexico at the age of thirteen for her stepfather's employment. She discusses her early life, education, different occupations, and her drive to better herself and give back to the community. She discusses her involvement in founding various Hispanic organizations in Indiana including Fiesta Indianapolis, Indiana Hispanic Chamber of Commerce, Hispanic Education Center, a Spanish speaking radio program, and Hispanic Hoosiers newsletter. Tapia discusses the history of Latino communities in Indiana and the hardships many Latino immigrants face all over the United States. She also discusses the importance of her Catholic faith.
  East Chicago, Indiana; Indianapolis, Indiana; Mexico; Catholicism; immigration; Latino communities; Hispanic Education Center; Hispanic Hoosiers; Diaz, Delia
- Valdez, Angela; Valdez, Gerardo, May 25, 2002; 02-067; Sharp, Ethan; 11 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index; transcribed in Spanish
  Angela Valdez and her husband, Gerardo Valdez, tell about their life histories and the evolution of their Catholic faith. They discuss their life in Mexico, their move to Los Angeles, and finally to Indianapolis, Indiana. The Valdezes discuss their involvement in St. Patrick Catholic Church, particularly in a charismatic prayer group. They address several details of their faith and discusses changes within the Catholic church.
  Indianapolis, Indiana; Los Angeles, California; Mexico; Catholic charismatics; Catholicism; immigration; Latino communities; migration; St. Patrick Catholic Church; Fox, Tom
- Vasquez, Francis, July 26, 2001; 02-057; Sharp, Ethan; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 40 minutes
  Francis Vasquez discusses immigration to the United States and Latino communities in central Indiana. He also talks about his faith.
  central Indiana; immigration; Latino communities; religious beliefs
- Woodburn, Soledad, March 26, 2002; 02-060; Sharp, Ethan; Not transcribed; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 90 minutes
  Soledad Woodburn discusses immigration and Latino communities. He also discusses his faith.